Finding Aid for Stewart, Van Akin and Seymour Family papers, 1829-2003
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Stewart, Van Akin and Seymour Family papers 1829-2003, 1860-1964
Stewart family
(in 2 boxes)
1.25 linear feet
2010078 Aa 2
Papers of the Stewart, Van Akin, and Seymour families, of Flint, Michigan. Includes correspondence, genealogies, newspaper clippings, family memorabilia and photographs.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Donated by Van Akin Burd (donor no. 8144 ) in 2010.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
The Stewart, Van Akin, and Seymour families were among the earliest settlers to Shiawassee County Michigan in the 1830s. James Van Akin (1794-1848) and his wife Elizabeth Jennings Van Akin moved to there from New York state in 1834. He and Elizabeth were farmers. They had eleven children, among them Henry Jennings Van Akin (1823-1896) who married Anne Stewart (1842-1884), also of Shiawassee County, Michigan.
Anne was the daughter of Addison Stewart (1811-1848) and his wife Lucy Tilden Stewart (1811-1898) who came to Michigan in 1833 from Avon, New York. Their other children included sons Charles (1839-1864) and Damon (1834-1867), who both served in the American Civil War, and daughters Harriett (Hattie) (b. 1836) and Laura (b. 1838). Damon served in the 23rd Michigan, company F and William served in Michigan's 23rd regiment, company C. Laura married Henry Seymour (d. 1899).
The Seymour family came to Michigan in the late 1830s when James Seymour relocated from Rochester, NY to Shiawassee County. Laura Stewart married his son Henry Seymour in the second half of the nineteenth century and they had five children. Their son James (b. 1864) married Elizabeth Graves Gilmore (1871-1947) and had a daughter Elizabeth Harriet Graves (1904-1970). Mary Seymour (1876-1964) was James's daughter from a previous marriage. Their daughter Hattie lived in Harpoot, Turkey in the late nineteenth century where she served as a missionary to the Armenians.
Melvin Van Akin Burd is the descendant of the Stewart and Van Akin/Jennings families through his great grandmother Anne Stewart and Henry Jennings Van Akin. He served in World War II and became an English professor at the State University of New York, Cortland. The Seymours are his cousins.
The collection consists of four series: Jennings-Van Akin-Burd, Tilden-Stewart, Stewart-Seymour, and Visual Materials. The strength of the collection lies in its documentation of the history of the Stewart and Seymour families, especially the family correspondence from the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
Subjects:
Armenians.; Missionaries--Turkey.; Missionaries--United States.; Seymour family.; Shiawassee County (Mich.); Stuart family.; Turkey.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 23rd (1862-1865). Company C.; United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 23rd (1862-1865). Company F.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Van Aken family.
Contributors:
Armstrong, Harriet Seymour.; Seymour, James.; Stewart, Charles, 1839-1864.; Stewart, Damon, 1834-1867.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Jennings-Van Akin-Burd
  The Jennings-Van Akin-Burd series contains material related to Melvin Van Akin Burd, especially his genealogical research, correspondence, and a memoir of his World War II military service. It also contains miscellaneous news clippings related to the Jennings family, and newsletters of the Van Aken/Van Auken family in the United States.
  - "Index to Individuals and Families Named Van Auken and Van Aken," by Robert A. Van Auken, Glorya E. Welch, and Florence L. Van Aken 1990 (Box 1)
  - Genealogies, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Jennings Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
  - Melvin Van Akin Burd
    - Correspondence 1930 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence circa 1990s (Box 1)
    - "Not a Hero: Recollections of My Military Duty on Okinawa, 1945" 2003 (Box 1)
    - Vital Records of Colrain, Massachusetts to the end of the year 1849, with notes by V. A. Burd, undated (Box 1)
      (photocopied material from 1908)
    - Genealogical Research, Newberry Library 1976, undated (Box 1)
  - Van Aken/Van Auken Newsletter 1995-2004 (scattered) (Box 1)
- Tilden-Stewart
  The Tilden-Stewart series contains genealogies, correspondence, and newspaper clippings related to the family of Addison Stewart and Lucy Tilden Stewart. Of particular interest is the Civil War correspondence of their sons Damon and William C. Stewart. The series also contains correspondence of Anne Stewart Van Akin, Melvin Van Akin Burd's grandmother, who married Henry Jennings Van Akin.
  - Tilden-Stewart Genealogies, 4 folders (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings (Box 1)
  - Anne Stewart Van Akin (Mrs. Henry Van Akin, daughter of Addison and Lucy Tilden Stewart)
    - Correspondence 1861-1876 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Obituaries 1884 (Box 1)
  - Damon Stewart (son of Addison Stewart and Lucy Tilden Stewart)
    - Correspondence 1861-1864 (Box 1)
      (includes letters written while Stewart was a soldier in the 23rd Michigan Volunteer Infantry, Company F)
  - Ellen Stewart
    - Correspondence 1859-1860 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence from Harpoot, Turkey 1886-1903 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Lucy Tilden Stewart (Mrs. Addison Stewart)
    - Genealogy undated (Box 1)
    - Memorabilia undated (Box 1)
  - William C. Stewart
    - Correspondence 1861-1862 (Box 1)
      (includes letters written while Stewart was a soldier in 23rd Michigan Volunteer Infantry, Company C)
    - Estate of 1865 (Box 1)
    - Newspaper clippings of death notice circa 1860s (Box 1)
- Stewart-Seymour
  The third series, Stewart-Seymour, documents the history of Henry Seymour and Laura Stewart Seymour, daughter of Addison Stewart and Lucy Tilden Stewart, and their children and grandchildren. Of particular interest is the correspondence from Harriet Seymour Armstrong while she was a missionary to the Armenians in Harpoot, Turkey. The series contains correspondence, genealogies, diaries, and miscellaneous memorabilia.
  - Ellen Seymour (daughter of Henry Seymour and Laura Stewart Seymour)
    - Correspondence 1895-1897 (Box 1)
  - Elizabeth Harriet Graves Seymour (daughter of James and Elizabeth Graves Gilmore Seymour)
    - Correspondence 1913-1964 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Memoirs and Genealogy 1902-1923 (scattered) and undated (Box 1)
  - Harriet (Hattie) Seymour Armstrong (daughter of Henry Seymour and Laura Stewart Seymour)
    - Correspondence 1893-1904 (Box 1)
  - Henry Seymour
    - Correspondence 1861-1897 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - Land Grants 1866-1867, 1869 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)
  - James Seymour
    - Correspondence 1884-1916 (Box 1)
    - Diaries, 1896, 1899 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1910-1943, undated (scattered), 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Laura Stewart Seymour (Mrs. Henry Seymour, daughter of Addison Stewart and Lucy Tilden Stewart)
    - Correspondence 1886-1904 (scattered) (Box 1)
  - Mary Seymour (daughter of James and Elizabeth Graves Gilmore Seymour)
    - Correspondence 1961, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous undated (Box 1)
    - Obituaries 1964 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1888, 1930, undated (Box 1)
  - Genealogies 1902, undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Genealogies (Box 2)
  - Seymour Land Grants 1836-1837 (Box 2)
- Visual Materials
  The final series, Visual Materials, mostly contains photographs of members of the Seymour family. There are also several drawings, and a few photographs from the Addison Stewart and Lucy Tilden Stewart line of the family.
  - Seymour Family Coat of Arms (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Miscellaneous Unidentified Family Members (Box 2)
    - Seymour Family
      - Elizabeth Graves Gilmore (Mrs. James Seymour) (Box 2)
      - Elizabeth Harriet Graves Seymour (daughter of James and Elizabeth Graves Seymour) (Box 2)
      - Emily Seymour (daughter of Henry and Laura Stewart Seymour) (Box 2)
      - Henry and Laura Seymour and children (Box 2)
      - James Seymour (son of Henry and Laura Stewart Seymour) (Box 2)
      - Laura Stewart Seymour (daughter of Addison Stewart and Lucy Tilden Stewart) (Box 2)
      - Mary Seymour (daughter of Henry and Laura Stewart Seymour) (Box 2)
      - Newbelia Elizabeth Graves Gilmore (mother of Elizabeth Graves Seymour) (Box 2)
      - Will Seymour (son of Henry and Laura Stewart Seymour) (Box 2)
    - Stewart Family
      - Frances McQuigg Stewart (Box 2)
      - Stewart Relics 1931 (Box 2)
  - Drawings
    - "Home" by Elizabeth G. Seymour 1858 (Box 2)
    - "The Flushing Home," by H. L. Brent and an unidentified drawing of a house undated (Box 2)